

Rémi Vezy

RESEARCHER

UMR AMAP, Bâtiment PS2, Boulevard de la Lironde, 34398 Montpellier, France

□+33 467 614 455 | ☑remi.vezy@cirad.fr | 希remivezy.com | ☑VEZY | ☐remivezy | УezyRemi

Professional Summary

I am a researcher working for CIRAD at the UMR AMAP lab in Montpellier, France. I am specialized on Functional-Structural Plant Modelling (FSPM), and my research interests include ecophysiology, environmental physics, tree architecture, computer models and agronomy.

Experience _____

CIRAD

Montpellier, France

RESEARCHER

01/10/2018 - Present

• Functional-structural plant modelling for agronomy, agroforestry and forestry

INRAEMontpellier, France

POST-DOCTORATE 03/2018 - 30/09/2018

• Modelling intercrops with the STICS soil-crop model: model adaptation for simulating intercrop management scenarios within the framework of the H2020 European project ReMIX

UMR ISPA - INRAE

Bordeaux, France

PHD in environmental physics 01/10/2014 - 31/12/2017

· Simulation of alternative management practices for the adaptation of perennial plantations to global changes

Education_

INRAE Centre de Recherche de Bordeaux-Aquitaine

Bordeaux

PHD IN ENVIRONMENTAL PHYSICS: SIMULATION OF ALTERNATIVE MANAGEMENT PRACTICES FOR THE ADAPTATION OF

2014 - 2017

PERENNIAL PLANTATIONS TO GLOBAL CHANGES

AgroParisTech

Master: Tropical ecosystem management, mathematics and modelling
Université Paul Sabatier

Kourou

2012 - 2013

Toulouse

First year Master's degree: Ecology
Université Paul Sabatier

Toulouse

Licence: Organisms, populations and ecosystems biology 2007 - 2011

Publications

SCIENTIFIC ARTICLES (A-RANK)

Noémie Gaudio, Gaëtan Louarn, Romain Barillot, Clémentine Meunier, Rémi Vezy...

in silico Plants

EXPLORING COMPLEMENTARITIES BETWEEN MODELLING APPROACHES THAT ENABLE UPSCALING FROM PLANT COMMUNITY FUNCTIONING TO ECOSYSTEM SERVICES AS A WAY TO SUPPORT AGROECOLOGICAL TRANSITION

2022

• Cites: 8

Raphaël PA Perez, Rémi Vezy, Loïc Brancheriau, Frédéric Boudon, François Gran...

in silico Plants

WHEN ARCHITECTURAL PLASTICITY FAILS TO COUNTER THE LIGHT COMPETITION IMPOSED BY PLANTING DESIGN: AN IN SILICO APPROACH USING A FUNCTIONAL-STRUCTURAL MODEL OF OIL PALM

2022

• Cites: 1

Grégoire Leclerc, Pierre Bommel, Natacha Motisi, Rémi Vezy, Edwin Treminio, J...

Agronomie, Environnement \& Soci{\'e}t{\'e}s

Coffee leaf rust (Hemeleia vastatrix) risk management in Central America: contribution of remote interactive simulations

2021

• Cites: 0

Rémi Vezy, Guerric le Maire, Fabien Charbonnier, Mathias Christina, Selena Ge	World Congress on Agroforestry
DynACof, a Model for Growth, Yield, Carbon, Water, Energy Balances and Ecosystem Services of Coffea in	
Agroforestry	2019
Mathias Christina, Guerric Le Maire, Yann Nouvellon, Remi Vezy, Bruno Bordron	Eucalyptus 2018
EUCALYPTUS PLANTATIONS AND DEEP GROUNDWATER: THE EFFECTS OF DIFFERENT POTASSIUM AND WATER SUPPLY REGIMES ON SOIL WATER UPTAKE AND WATER TABLE DEPTH	2018
Olivier Roupsard, Karel Van Den Meersche, Clementine Allinne, Philippe Vaast,	World Coffee Summit
EIGHT YEARS STUDYING ECOSYSTEM SERVICES IN A COFFEE AGROFORESTRY OBSERVATORY. PRACTICAL APPLICATIONS FOR THE	2017
R. Vezy, M Christina, O. Roupsard, Y Nouvellon, F. Charbonnier, J. P. Laclau,	Functional Ecology Conference
MODELLING PLANT TO PLOT ENERGY BALANCE AFTER IMPROVING THE MAESPA MODEL IN SIMPLE TO COMPLEX FORESTS AND	2017
AGROFORESTS R. Vezy, D. Picart, M Christina, M. Soma, S. Georgiou, F. Charbonnier, D Lous	European Agroforestry Conference
EFFECT OF SHADE ON TEMPERATURE MITIGATION AND CANOPY ASSIMILATION OF COFFEE AGROFORESTRY SYSTEMS: A	2016
MODELLING APPROACH	Conference on Agricultural and
R. Vezy, D. Picart, M. Christina, M. Soma, S. Georgiou, F. Charbonnier, D. Lo	Forest Meteorology
COUPLING A 3D LIGHT INTERCEPTION WITH A GROWTH AND YIELD MODEL TO ADJUST SHADE LEVEL IN COFFEE AGROFORESTRY SYSTEMS SIMULATED UNDER CLIMATE CHANGE MANUSCRIPTS	2016
R. Vezy	
SIMULATION DE PRATIQUES DE GESTION ALTERNATIVES POUR LADAPTATION DES PLANTATIONS PERENNES AUX CHANGEMENTS GLOBAUX	2017
R. Vezy	
Understand and protect endemism: application to the case of the (semi-) evergreen forests of the western	2013
GHATS.	
Books	
Rémi Vezy Le Compagnon de L'utilisateur R Olivier Roupsard, Clémentine Allinne, Karel Van Den Meersche, Philippe Vaast, Suivi des services ecosystemiques dans un observatoire de cafeiers agroforestiers. Applications pour la filiere du cafe	in progress 2019
Projects	
PALMSTUDIO-2	Link
R. Vezy (CIRAD)	2020-2022
• Modelling performances of oil palm plantation by identification of architectural and functionnal traits, secon	nd phase
PALMSTUDIO	Link
J. Dauzat (CIRAD) • Modelling performances of oil palm plantation by identification of architectural and functionnal traits	2017-2019
ARBRATATOUILLE II	Link
AGROOF Improvement of agroforestry technical itineraries in vegetable production	2014-
ReMIX	Link
E. Justes (INRAE) Redesigning European cropping systems based on species MIXtures	2017-2021
EUCFLUX C. LE MAIDE (CIDAD), V. NOUNELLON (CIDAD), A. DODIN (CIDAD), L. D. LAGLAN (CIDAD), L. CHINA ENGE (CIDAD)	Link
 G. Le Maire (CIRAD), Y. Nouvellon (CIRAD), A. Robin (CIRAD), J-P. Laclau (CIRAD), J. Guillemot (CIRAD) Quantification of the Carbon, Water and Nutrient Balances at Ecosystem Scale, for a Rotation of the Eucalyp 	2008-2017 otus using Flux tower
ANR MACCAC	Link
O. ROUPSARD (CIRAD) Modélication pour l'accompagnement des ACtours yers l'Adaptation des Couverts pérannes ou agreforaction	2014-2017
 Modélisation pour l'accompagnement des ACteurs, vers l'Adaptation des Couverts pérennes ou agroforestie COFFEEFLUX 	ers aux Changements globaux Link
O. ROUPSARD (CIRAD)	2009-2018
• Measuring and modelling carbon, nutrients, water and sediment Ecosystem Services in an agroforestry coff	fee watershed (Costa Rica)

Software development	
DynACof	Link
R language	2016 - today
The Dynamic Agroforestry Coffee Crop Model	
MAESPA	Link
FORTRAN	2014 - today
Maespa is a model of forest canopy radiation absorption, photosynthesis and water balance	
sticRs	Link
R language	2018
The R package for the STICS model	
STICS-intercrop	Link
FORTRAN	2018-today
Simulateur mulTldisciplinaire pour les Cultures Standard.	
sticsRpacks	Link
RLANGUAGE	2018-today
Suite of R packages for STICS	
VPALM-IDE	Link
Rlanguage	2018-today
• A shiny application bundled in an Electron application to compute virtual palm scenes from architectural data	
VPALMr	Link
R language	2018-today
R package to build palm tree mockups from field data	
archimedR	Link
R language	2018-today
A Package To Manage ARCHIMED Simulations	

Languages_

French native

ENGLISHgoodPORTUGUESEbasic conversationSPANISHvery basic